[Music]
so
hello hello good evening good day how
are you doing i hope you're doing all
all doing great
welcome to the latest episode of ask
abidjit
uh today we are discussing science
technology and all of that good stuff
so before we begin let me greet all of
you let's see who all is there i can see
aditya tulsi
and lots of other people lots of other
people good evening good day all of you
wherever you are great to have you all
on the show
so we will discuss science technology
and
related matters today so let us begin
with the questions
and what is the first question
right the first question is appropriate
for what's happening right now the james
webb space telescope
so a lot of people have asked me
questions about this i've taken a few
which represent all the questions
hopefully
so uh swatha says how do you feel about
analyzing the mind-blowing images from
the jwst any new findings more details
on the universe would be great amruta
says the jwst
showed
the most stunning images both all
inspiring and intimidating what are your
thoughts as an astrophysicist do you
feel we are really mature enough to
understand this phenomena
um pratham says the james webb telescope
captured in astonishing
phenomena images
can it really time travel
how do we do time traveling is it going
back in time or going to a different
location
running where the clocks are running
slower than earth and so on yeah
so lots of people have asked me about
this because it's something that's
happened very recently
nasa has
this week i believe released images a
bunch of images four or five images that
the james webb space telescope is taken
the first batch of images have been
released let's take a look at the images
and let's see what uh they are telling
us
so this is let me ah i hope you can all
hear me this is the instagram account of
the james webb telescope nasa web is the
account id or whatever it's called
and as you can see it has released a
bunch of new images i think there are
five images there is a spectrum of an
exoplanet and there's something more
so let's take a look at what the jade so
so what is the jwst what is the james
webb space telescope it's a new
telescope it's a much
more powerful space telescope than the
previous one that nasa had put up which
was the hubble the hubble went into
orbit i believe in the 1990s if i'm not
mistaken
the hubble is still functional it's in
orbit around the earth
the james webb space telescope is not in
orbit around the earth it's in orbit
around the l2 lagrange point which is
about a million i think kilometers from
the earth
uh so it's directly between it's
directly behind
the earth as in a straight line with the
sun so if you take the sun in the earth
straight line jwst is right behind that
about a million kilometers approximately
from the earth roughly
uh so it's in the shade of the earth it
doesn't see the sun that's why it's cool
it stays cool
so this temper this uh
telescope it is designed to remain
extremely cool so that it can detect
very cold infrared wavelengths and
that's why it's able to peer much deeper
into space and essentially time travel
so let me get get back to you after in a
moment about what the time travel thing
means so this is one of the instruments
okay this is the spectrograph the near
infrared spectrograph so this
spectrograph at a single time it can
take spectra from hundreds of targets at
the same time and as you can see these
are all these lines these horizontal
lines are spectra what is a spectrum
it's like a
it's like a light signature it's like a
light library that comes from one source
what are the different chemical elements
present in that light source and so on
so that is something you can see from
the spectrum
so this instrument can take
can capture infrared spectra from
hundreds of targets at the same time so
that's one of the great very interesting
capabilities of the jwst
this is a new uh
release
this is
the spectrum i believe
a spectrum of an exoplanet so which
exoplanet it is it is the exoplanet wasp
96b and it has detected the unmistakable
unambiguous signature of water which
indicates that there are clouds in this
exoplanet now this is a this is an
exoplanet called a hot jupiter it's very
close to its star
it uh
it
orbits its star i think once in three or
so earth days it's a very very tight
orbit it's a very hot star 1000 degrees
so no about 500 600 degrees celsius i
think the details are here yeah
and yeah so it's able to it's been able
to detect water in the atmosphere of
this planet that's interesting
this is a very interesting image this is
called stefan's quintet five galaxies
locked together i think four of these
galaxies are actually colliding at the
same time they're interacting
gravitationally this is a gravitational
dance between four galaxies and there's
a fifth fifth object as well in this
so four galaxies essentially colliding
in very very slow motion this collision
will go go on for maybe over a billion
years
eventually i believe
there could be the output of the of the
collision could be a merger and a new
massive galaxy
so this is what that looks like through
the lens through the eyes of the james
webb space telescope
these are some
images of of jupiter
that the telescope has taken in infrared
light i believe
this is a very interesting image
this is the deepest sharpest infrared
image ever taken at the universe
and this
so what what is how do we put this image
in context
so imagine you have
a grain of sand
a single grain of sand
you put it in front of you and you look
at the sky
the amount of sky that this one grain of
sand is able to blot out
that
is
what is in this image that's how small
it is that's how deep this telescope has
been able to look so this is nothing but
a small fraction of the hubble deep
ultra deep field
and it's able to uh look at this in
unprecedented detail right now what else
do we have we have this uh i think it's
called what is this called cat sign
southern ring nebula it's a it's a
southern ring nebula it's a planetary
nebula this is what happens when a star
dies when a sun like star
gives off its outer layers of gas this
is what happens
our sun will eventually meet this fate
so we still have the star in the center
it has given off all of its much of its
outer layers
it became a red giant and eventually the
the outer layers just went off because
the sun was the star was not able to
hold them together
so this is what happens so this is
unprecedented detail once again
and this is the cosmic cliffs part of
the karina nebula once again
unprecedented detail so now how do we
put these images in the right context is
what we have to think about so
the best way of putting these images in
the correct context is to compare them
with the images
that the hubble spell space telescope
gave us so let me share that and let's
do a comparison
to understand
the true power of this tale of the new
telescope
so this is a comparison all right the
james webb space telescope versus hubble
so let me
bigify this enlarge and begin this yeah
so this is what hubble showed us
very interesting nice image a lot of
detail and now see what the james webb
telescope is able to do look at the
extraordinary amount of detail the james
webb space telescope is uncovered it's
like a short-sighted person putting on
glasses for the first time and suddenly
you can see the world in
its real
depth and sharpness so that's that's how
it is
so as you can see the hubble image which
i believe is in visible light
is quite opaque the clouds the clouds
are quite opaque you can't really see
the see through the clouds but because
the jwst operates in infrared
wavelengths it can peer through the
clouds and see what's inside
and that's what you see in much greater
depth sharpness in resolution so this is
the karina nebula
let's see what else we have
so this is the other
nebula that we spoke about
this is what hubble showed us very nice
image very interesting
now see what the jwst has done
incredible detail
incredible detail we can see right
through the clouds and see what's behind
and see far more depth and resolution
of this image then this is the stefan
squintet that we spoke about
this is what hubble showed us
this is the hubble image let me uh yeah
now you should be able to see it
properly this is the image from hubble
as you can see the night sky is quite
dark we don't see much detail and here
we see way more detail look at that
we can see way more detail about what's
happening here so that's the
amount of detail the jwst is able to
show us and this is just the beginning
this is the beginning this is the hubble
image of the ultra deep field as you can
see lot of detail lot of galaxies but
see what the james webb telescope has
done
incredible amount of sharpness and way
more detail
and what you see here is these various
galaxies that are all smeared out
and squashed and and
you know the shapes are distorted this
is called gravitational lensing in which
unseen matter essentially dark matter
acts as a lens as a
just like an optical lens does and it
shows you what's behind and shows you
things in a more magnified manner and of
course it produces distortion of light
because when you have a certain amount
of mass mass massive amount of mass in
space
light has to go around it light cannot
travel in a straight line because the
the mass curves space time itself
general relativity so this is what you
see
this is a an exemplification of that
and so on so these are the images from
the james webb telescope revolution
revolutionary images very
great detail unprecedented detail
and uh so exciting we're gonna see this
is just the beginning this is just a
small sampler
amuse bush it's it's a it's a starter
before the main course before the main
meal so uh this is the kind of detail
this telescope is able to show us now
what about time travel why do we why do
some people say it's a time traveling
telescope it's not going back in time
what is what it is doing is this
see um
when
when the uni initially
in the initial moment of the big bang
all of the universe was just energy
and about 250 million or so years after
the big bang um the universe first
became transparent and light was able to
shine for the first time so that is the
first initial light the after glow of
the big bang you could call it yeah
and that was very hot light the universe
was quite small at the time compared to
what to the size it is now
so the radiation the after glow of the
big bang was high frequency light hot
light
as the universe expanded and cooled the
light was stretched out it was red
shifted
and the oldest light in the universe is
now extremely extremely
it's no longer visible
it's uh the cmb are the cosmic microwave
background edition is in the millimeter
uh
range here that sort of those sort of
frequencies wavelengths millimeter
wavelengths and the oldest light in the
universe is is
redshifted so badly that it's
undetectable to regular telescopes like
the hubble telescope and your backyard
astronomer telescopes and so on so
in order to detect that ancient light
we need something like the hubble like
the jwst
and to detect that it has to be kept
very very cold because infrared light is
heat
it's heat
right so uh it needs to be incredibly
cold and that's why it's been placed at
the l2 lagrange point in the shade of
the earth so that the sun's rays don't
reach there it remains cold and that's
why it's able to detect this very very
ancient and very faint and very cold
light
and that's why it's going to be able to
show us
images essentially what of what could be
the first objects that were visible in
the universe
you know the first the very first
galaxies the very first structure
formation in the universe and so on
that's why we say it's traveling back in
time because it's showing us images of
the universe
that are like more than 13.5 billion
years old so we are looking back in time
that's why
we say it's a time travelling school
it's not really going back in time it's
showing us it's going to show us uh
pictures images of the universe as it
was a long long long long time ago in
its very infancy so that's why it's
called
well it's typically journalists
who come up with these names time
traveling telescope god particle all
that stuff
they're not scientific names but yeah
these names catch on even the big bang
was a i think i don't know who came up
with it i think it was fred hoyle or
somebody who coined this
slightly
derogatory name but it's stuck and
generally it caught on among the
journalistic fraternity and that's why
it's part of popular imagination now
anyhow so that's a little bit about the
james webb space telescope
uh
looking forward to more data coming in
there's so much more
science that this telescope is going to
do
it's going to revolutionize astronomy
revolutionize hopefully our
understanding of the universe maybe
throw light on so many uh hidden aspects
how was the universe in the very
beginning
what is dark matter who knows we may
even get get to understand that better
understanding exoplanets what they are
like the composition the spectral
compositions the atmospheric composition
of exoplanet of exoplanets maybe even
some solar system astronomy
understanding jupiter saturn etc our own
solar system better that also will
happen and so on so it's just the
beginning a very exciting phase
in astronomy and physics astrophysics
right question number two is by shubham
can green hydrogen be used as a fuel in
the future what are your thoughts on
green hydrogen all right green hydrogen
so first of all my dear friends let's
understand this is not hydrogen that is
green in color all right
hydrogen is colorless as far as i know
it is colorless yes
what do you mean by green hydrogen
green hydrogen is hydrogen that is
produced
using renewable energy sustainable
energy which doesn't have a so
essentially the hydrogen that is
produced without uh
causing a carbon footprint what do you
mean what do we mean by that
so how is hydrogen typically uh produced
commercially industrially etc
it is
produced
via electrolysis of water
water as i am sure
you all know is its chemical
formula composition is h2o two atoms of
a hydrogen and one atom of oxygen come
together to form the oxy to form the
water molecule h2o molecule right
so if you have
water you pass an electric current
through it
then you have a process called
electrolysis which dissociates the
molecules into their component atoms
and that gives off oxygen
and hydrogen now there are processes of
separating these two things and we need
to be careful because hydrogen is a very
flammable gas
and so
that's how it's done
and the reverse process happens in
rocket engines there are certain rocket
engines which use uh
hydrogen fuel and oxygen fuel you bring
them together
exothermic reaction very enormously
exothermic reaction and the output of
that is just water vapor extremely high
pressure high temperature water vapor
yeah so
so electrolysis is the elec is the this
the process of dissociating water into
hydrogen and oxygen by passing electric
current through it that's what
electrolysis is now typically
electricity is produced by burning
fossil fuels either by burning coal or
burning gas or whatever else
so all electricity most of the
electricity that we use today has a
carbon footprint you need to release co2
carbon dioxide into the atmosphere to
produce this electricity
however if you produce electricity
through renewable
sources like wind power hydropower solar
electricity etc then it has a what you
could call a negligible or or almost
zero carbon footprint so if you take
such electricity that is produced
through sustainable means
and you use that
to
produce hydrogen from from water through
electrolysis that is what we call green
hydrogen because it doesn't have carbon
footprint and we are
it isn't the production of such hydrogen
does not uh cause harm to the planet it
does not uh
add to the carbon burden
of the planet in the atmosphere right so
that is what we mean by green hydrogen
now hydrogen is a very good fuel
very good fuel it's used in rocket
engines so you can see how energetic it
can be yeah the specific impulse or
whatever you call it uh
is is very high compared to uh fossil
fuels like uh gasoline petrol kerosene
which is aviation fuel diesel and so on
so uh it can certainly be used and uh
engines can be can be uh
produced which use hydrogen as fuel
uh so yeah it's it's it's a promising
fuel
you would need to tweak certain
technologies in order to use hydrogen
maybe liquid hydrogen i mean there are
challenges
uh keeping hydrogen in the liquid state
uh requires a lot of well it's a
cryogenic fuel right which means it's a
very low temperature fuel you need to
refrigerate it to very low temperatures
i'm not sure what is the the
boiling point of hydrogen which is the
point at which its liquid form turns
into gas but it's a very low temperature
so to keep it liquid you would need to
have pressurized canisters at low
temperatures yeah because the pressure
is very high and so on so these are
challenges but yes it can certainly be
used if you develop the technologies
developing technology typically takes a
few years
and all technological uh obstacles can
be overcome with engineering
so i think if you can produce hydrogen
in a sustainable
fashion without adding to the carbon
footprint without adding to the carbon
burden of the planet of the atmosphere
then it's a very promising fuel
so i think it's it's a promising fuel i
think india is taking
significant amounts of initiatives
uh vis-a-vis green hydrogen so i think
it's great india i think it's
essentially
in some ways it's leading the world in
in
moving to
green technologies and sustainable
energy sources the solar alliance india
is the founding member of that alliance
and uh we have uh
we have uh
we we have stated
that we will move entirely to to
sustainable sources of energy by 20 2070
2070 or so right that's the statement
that's been made so i think we could be
very much on track to do that takes time
but we need to develop this technology
step by step
and i think it's very promising so yeah
so these are my thoughts about green
hydrogen
right aditi says our body recognizes
anything foreign that enters our body
and starts to attack it that's what the
immune system does yes
but what about food
food is also foreign even though it's
essential for us why doesn't our body
attack it too
this is a very good question this is a
very good question excellent question
good to see intelligent questions
right
so you are right aditi that uh
you
anything foreign any foreign object
that enters our body is immediately
attacked let's say you are doing
woodworking you know carpentry and the
splinter of wood gets into your hand
it's very painful very annoying and you
can see very quickly a reaction you know
the entire
part of the skin around that flesh turns
red and there's a swelling and then
eventually if you don't remove it there
will be formation of pus which is
the the byproduct of the immune
attack on that system and eventually the
thing will be expelled in the body the
the that part of the body will heal
itself rapidly so that is the very
visible
immune reaction attack attack the
foreign object
and as you say food is foreign to us so
one of the examples of
this immune attack on foreign objects is
when somebody
receives an organ transplant a kidney or
a heart or a lung or whatever it is
right
the the immune system attack on this
these foreign objects foreign organs
even though they are vital to your
survival is very true it's very real and
because of this very real phenomenon
people have to be given
immunosuppressant drugs entire cocktails
of drugs in order to keep the immune
system prevent the immune system from
destroying that uh the transplanted
organ yes so it is true that anything
foreign that enters the body is
immediately recognized by the immune
system as something foreign and it is
attacked and it is destroyed
take no enemies destroy it that's how it
is
and yet we eat food
so why doesn't uh so what happens when
we eat food okay let's say i take a
carrot i don't have one right now for
demonstration purposes but let's say i'm
eating a carrot what do we do with the
carrot we put it on in our mouth and we
start attacking it right away chew chew
chew chew we chew it chew it chew it
right we chew it down we mash it up it
mixes with our saliva which is enzymes
which break up the food
we swallow it inside our food inside of
our stomach we have acid
hydrochloric acid which further destroys
that food and breaks it apart right and
we have enzymes and then it it's
transferred to our
small intestine and large intestine
everything of value is taken out of the
food it is totally destroyed
right so isn't that what happens
so what
is done
is that anything that is potentially
harmful in the food is neutralized
let's say you eat a carrot that you have
not washed god forbid
the gods forbid
don't eat a carrot that you got from the
market you did not wash it you did not
remove the skin possibly and maybe there
are harmful bacteria that on the carrot
you eat the carrot you chew it up all
those bacteria will go inside they will
be taken care of by the immune system
right the immune system will neutralize
anything and sometimes when you eat
something and there are too many
bacteria or certain evil bacteria
salmonella etc then for some time you
get food poisoning because they kind of
overwhelm the immune system for a while
before the immune system takes over and
wipes them out
so
anytime you eat food all the same immune
responses happen
everything every
molecule of the food is scrutinized by
the immune system
and it is checked it is its passport and
visa is checked essentially do you have
anything harmful on you a thorough a
thorough screening is done and only when
it's just
in just molecules and in proteins and
phytochemicals and all those things
only then is it allowed to pass through
if something harmful is there it is
destroyed annihilated neutralized
right
so yes the same checks
are done even when we eat food but
there's a whole different system we
don't take a sliver of carrot and we
don't put it into our into our flesh we
send it through the right
uh
in the right in the right way right
through new process the new process is
to put it in your mouth and do swallow
it and chew it follow it have it
digest and so on so if you do it through
the new process to the proper approved
procedure then
the proper checks and balances are done
but if you take a piece of carrot or
apple or whatever and you shove it into
your skin it will meet the exact same
immune response as a sliver of wood wood
meat
and similarly if you eat wood you chew
it properly or you take sawdust and you
eat it it won't meet the same immune
response as it would need if you were to
shove it inside your palm
right so the immune system of course has
all the same checks and balances
i mean the digestive system has all the
same immunological checks and balances
the immune system takes very good care
to ensure that nothing harmful gets into
the body either through the stomach
lining or through the user or
through the lining alveolar alveolar
lining of the intestines and so on at
every single step there are checks and
balances everything is taken care of
so that's how it works it's a very
interesting complicated process even
biology is incredibly fascinating
incredibly fascinating so yeah that is
in brief the answer it's a very
intelligent question you've asked i
it's good to see that good job
okay balu says
what do you think about the future where
we will be living in the metaverse well
that is still to be seen whether we will
be living in the metaverse the metaverse
creators would like us all to live in
the matter so what is this metaverse
thing what is it
the metaverse is this imaginary world
which we can access through virtual
reality headsets those bulky things that
you wear on your on your eyes and then
you go into a different world and then
they want you to live there for hours
and hours and hours and purchase a real
estate that is imaginary
and essentially live in this augmented
reality so right now the the virtual
reality headsets that are available why
are various uh meta worth creating
companies so
who are these
creators of the metaverse there are like
it's a bunch of
extremely large extremely powerful and
extremely wealthy corporations
all in the us
who want to change the world
they want to change the world they want
to change the way we live
they want to change our lifestyles they
want to change the way we interact with
data with information they want to
change the way we spend our time all of
that
that is the metaverse so
one of them is meta they have changed
their name from facebook to meta in
to to be in line with their that push
towards in in this coming decade to make
the metaverse the reality so the
metabours is
virtual reality and augmented reality so
right now the headsets that we have to
wear are very bulky
you wear that for more than an hour i
think you get a headache it's that bulky
but they are working on the technology
to make it lighter and lighter
eventually it will be just like wearing
glasses right so you wear those glasses
and you will see the same world but you
will see augmented reality so you will
see extra data on that so right now i
you just see a few books around behind
me over here you can see that
you wear those glasses each of in you
you can choose any book let's say this
blue one here and they do something and
it will show me right away without
opening the book who's the author how
many pages how many words etc etc etc
metadata
that is one example
you go
go for a walk
wearing those vr
glasses and you will see information
about every single store what is the
store about how long has it been open or
what is the average uh monthly
income that they make or
and so on
so is there anything that is of use to
you or of interest to you it will show
you all of that so you don't have to go
and talk to people anymore you will get
all the data right away that is one
example the other thing is living in
virtual reality reality you have games
like minecraft which is a virtual
illusionary world you have games like
platforms like roblox
and so on
you have a role-playing games in which
you you immerse yourself in the
environment and you become a warrior or
something so eventually they would want
this to be available at uh
at your fingertips tips on demand and
eventually that would you would not even
perhaps need
glasses for that you may
use contact lenses or eventually even
neural implants
to have that on demand as long as you
pay the monthly subscription
eventually you may even get custom
designed dreams if you wish or whatever
so all of this is the metavirus
it's it's something that they it's an
artificial
virtual world
that they want to super impose on the
current world
and
obviously the thing is this
uh they they are uh
how they want to sell it is by showing
us the good uh effect of that like you
can sit at home
and pretend like you're in office and
talk to your colleagues as if you're in
the same room but you're actually in
your bedroom or in your office at home
or whatever right that sort of thing so
you don't you no longer have to go to
office you can be like you're in the
office and you will have virtual avatars
that represent you with your real face
and you can talk to your colleagues etc
and work together collaboratively and so
on there are obviously problems right
now like the time lag when it comes to
internet communication and so on but
they are working on these things and
eventually they would want to solve all
these problems so they are saying that
it
it makes it easier for you to work will
make it happen it is it will be much
easier for your kids to learn
you your kids could be at home and still
be in school they could
read books on demand they could
learn
information sitting
at home and so on but
the real monetization the real
commercial value is is in the games and
all that
so uh essentially they would like to
hook
kids into this
they would like to hook kids into the
metaphors uh it is easier to form habits
as you when you're a kid as opposed to
when you are much older which is why you
will see uncles and aunties
no offense
you know people who are 40 plus et
cetera who will not be really interested
in the metabolism but people were
teenagers essentially or even
kids in their in their in their first
decade of life they
take up technology so easily like fish
to water it is the this
a specific cohort the specific
generation generation z
generation said that they want to hook
into this
which is where the commercial value lies
because they will be able to eventually
monetize everything commercialize every
single aspect of the metaverse you can
even buy virtual real estate in the
metaphors now so that is what the future
is i don't think it's necessarily a very
good thing
the real world is the real world that is
the real physical world we live in we
can pretend like we're in a virtual
reality and pretend like we are
superheroes and all but at the end of
the day if you if you spend so much time
in in some illusory world while sitting
in the dark corner of your bedroom on a
blanket you're going to neglect your
health and you're going to have shorter
and shorter life and it's not going to
be good for you you're going to have
mental issues emotional issues what not
so i don't think it's a good thing they
want to enrich themselves at the expense
of the rest of the world i don't think
it's a good thing technology is a
double-edged sword it has good
uh
it has good applications and
applications that are not good for
everyone
so uh even the metaverse is the same
thing
there are pros and cons
but that's what it is like the the
battle is still to be fought right now
the technologies are still uh
in their infancy
but by the time this decade is out the
technologies will have developed they
will have matured and they will be like
well very attractive
to people
so let us see how it goes but i think it
may not necessarily be a very good thing
for for everybody
it will be certainly good for the
corporations but for the rest of the
world not so
convinced
they just says how do we see viruses
under electron microscopes when viruses
are smaller than the wavelength of light
for us to see anything the light must
reflect back from the surface right
does that mean electrons behave the same
way as light this is a good question so
what is light what is all that so light
is uh photons
visible light has a certain wavelength
and as they just says
viruses are extremely small
particles that are much smaller than the
wavelength of visible light
so
how does this work
so even see you must have heard of
something called quantum mechanics wave
particle duality every particle
can behave like a wave every wave can
essentially have all have a particle
nature
and uh
so that way even the electron which is a
essentially a point particle of sorts it
has a wavelength we know what the mass
of the electron is
and and we know what is the very simple
wavelength of
formula
for the wavelength of a massive particle
lambda is equal to h over p where h is
the planck constant p is the momentum
which
essentially means that lambda is equal
to lambda the wavelength so lambda is
equal to h upon m v
lambda is the wavelength h is planck's
constant m is the mass v is the velocity
right and if you fire electrons at a
certain speed what you at a certain
velocity what you find that the
wavelength of these electrons
can be around a hundred thousand times
shorter shorter than the wavelength of
visible light photons
one lakh times shorter
so that way the resolution
of the image that you will get out of
this is 100 000 times
better
and that's why we are able to see
viruses under uh these
by using electrons instead of photons
for probing the surfaces
for probing the the surface of the virus
that's why we are able to get good
images in electron microscopes so what
the electron microscope does is that it
fires a beam i i see i don't know if the
exact uh
engineering mechanics and and
the the way
electron microscopes are built but i
know it conceptually
from the perspective of physics so what
you do is you fire a beam of electrons
at the target
right those electrons i suppose reflect
back and you would get a reading and
based on the reading you can create a
a map of the object that you're uh
trying to probe and that map essentially
is the image that you see with your eyes
so that way you can see things that
visible light can never ever show you
because you're using electrons as waves
not as particles as waves
so yes electrons do behave the same way
as light the photons are packets of
energy they are particles
and they are also waves their frequency
and wavelength similarly electrons also
have frequency and wavelength this is
the quantum wave particle duality in
action in real action we actually use
that in technology electron microscopes
are a great example of that
so it's not light it's electrons it's
electrons used as light
and that's how we're able to see things
that
regular visible light would never ever
show us
that's
in brief
how it works
karun says
what will be the fastest future
transports and ways to travel in space
after maybe a half a century or 100 or
100 years
can we achieve the speed higher than ten
thousand a hundred thousand kilometers
per hour for traveling
and what i have used on jeff bezos
anti-aging startup being immortal is
really possible okay
so
what is the speed of light 300 000
kilometers per second yes 300 000
kilometers per second you're talking
about 100 000 kilometers per hour
so that is much slower than that is it
possible yes it is possible and this
could could could happen soon i suppose
there is this project called
breakthrough star shot
which is going to use light sail
technology
two
and the objective is to have a large
number of small spacecraft micro
spacecraft maybe you know just a small
little thing
which will have a light sail and it will
have a very small chip that will with
with optical sensors etc
you're going to use pulsed laser laser
light
you're going to shine this laser light
on the light sails
and these micro spacecraft there may be
thousands of these will be accelerated
using a radiation pressure of the lasers
to a speed that may be
maybe a third of that of light maybe one
third light speed
and using this incredible
speed that we'll be able to achieve
we will be able to send these
this entire massive armada fleet of
spacecraft microspacecraft to our
nearest neighboring star system alpha
central proxima centauri
and
we could have these spacecraft visit one
of the exoplanets that's known to be
in orbit around the system and so this
process will take 20 to 30 years maybe
40 years
within 30 to 40 years
these spacecraft
traveling at nearly a third of the speed
of light will be able to reach our
neighboring star in just 30 or so years
and then they will take images data etc
photographs etc and and beam it back to
earth which will take about four years
four four and a half years
so within half a century
we will have actual images of an
exoplanet in
our neighboring star system which is
about four and a half for roughly four
and a half light years away from here
so this
will hap this is possible the technology
almost exists today
the phased laser array etc needs to be
worked on but once the technology is
available we will be actually able to do
that
so this could happen within a decade
within within a decade we will have
spacecraft tiny spacecraft
that can be accelerated to nearly a
third of the speed of light
or something like that roughly
yeah
relativistic velocities
so this is a
technology demonstration on a small
scale when you are building a fighter
plane you first develop a small model
which is an exact replica of what the
large thing will look like you test it
in a wind tunnel and you check out how
it works and so on so that is a
technology demonstration using that you
can improve upon it about the design
so similarly this is going to be a
technology demonstration on a small
scale of tiny spacecraft you know tiny
little spacecraft micro spacecraft but
the same principle will work just as
well on large spacecraft with massive
light sales kill kilometers square
kilometers in size
but you would need much more powerful
lasers to to accelerate such large
spacecraft to
relativistic velocities so in the next
100 years definitely possible
yeah traveling at relativistic
velocities is definitely possible if uh
we're able to develop the
technologies needed for that essentially
powerful enough lasers
very much possible
so that is your answer and what about
jeff bezos anti-aging startup is being
immortal really possible
being immortal
as far as i understand is not possible
you can certainly extend extend the
lifespan of the of you of human beings
right now the uh
in developed countries the average life
expectancy is around 80 80 to 83 in
japan which i think is adc 84.
it's between 70 to 85 years something
like that in developed countries in
other countries with
lower living standards you have lower
life expectancy and so on so forth right
so it is certainly
possible to extend the lifespan of a
human being using various processes
i've spoken about this before
it seems to be that aging the process of
aging is caused by the shortening
shortening of telomeres
at the ends of human chromosomes
so
a chromosome is essentially something
that carries part of your dna part of
your genome at the ends of your
chromosomes inside your body inside your
cells you have something called
telomeres
now as a person grows older
in years this the length of the
telomeres at the ends of the chromosomes
it gets shorter and this seems to be in
intrinsically connected to the process
of aging so it is theorized that if you
can stop the shortening of the telomere
then the process of aging can be
possibly uh
slowed down possibly even
stopped possibly we don't know
so there are some startups working on
that and i if i'm not mistaken maybe
jeff bezos and his startup is also
working on this particular uh
theory
that if you can
stop
the shortening of the telomeres then you
could possibly stop aging possibly stop
aging i don't think it would give a
person infinite lifespan i don't think
so maybe you could add 10 20 possibly
even 50 years to the human lifespan if
you can get this done
well if you can make this work it may
also
lead to improvements in brain health
possibly things like dementia and
alzheimer's disease etc could possibly
be uh
could possibly be treated or or even
prevented with this we don't know yet so
this research is still you could call it
in the initial phases initial stages
possibly in its infancy
so uh
i think it is certainly going to be
possible to extend
human lives by maybe 10 20 30 possibly
even 50 years
being immortal i think it's
impossible immortal means infinite and
infinity is unphysical
what is an infinity it's division by
zero that's unphysical so i don't think
it would be possible
ever to have an infinite lifespan
yeah
but uh yeah an extension of human lives
is certainly possible in terms of years
so
yeah it's something they're working on
okay karan says is it possible to make
anti-matter weapons anti-matter so
that's interesting so what is antimatter
i think we deal with a lot of antimatter
these days on this
show what's antimatter antivirus
particles are the uh
are are the
they are the same they have the same
mass as their regular matter
counterparts but they have opposite
charges
like for instance the positron which is
the antimatter equivalent of the
electron has the same mass as the
electron but electrons have negative
charge positrons have positive charge
antiprotons are again the same thing the
same mass as the regular protons but
opposite electric charges and so on so
that's one way of looking at antimatter
right so antimatter has been produced in
uh
various
linear colliders atom smashers like the
lhc et cetera yes it is certainly
possible to create antimatter and the
thing about antimatter matter is that if
antimatter comes into contact with the
regular matter it immediately
annihilates so let's say one
antihydrogen atom comes into contact
with a regular hydrogen atom there is
going to be an immediate annihilation
and all that is released is pure energy
pure energy
uh so that's what it is so let's say you
have one gram
of matter
and one gram of antimatter and you are
able to
get the two of these two uh
grams of matter antimatter to annihilate
completely it's going to give off
about 10 raised to 14 joules of energy
and its equivalent is about 40 to 45
kilotons equivalent of tnt
what does this mean
40 to 45 kilotons equivalent of tnt
comparison
the hiroshima
nuclear disaster with the hiroshima
nuclear weapon
gave off
a yield of 15
kilotons equivalent of tnt 15
the nagasaki
event the nagasaki war crime
it gave off
uh a yield of about 21 or 22 kilotons of
tnt
hiroshima 15 kilotons nagasaki 22
kilotons one gram of matter one gram of
antimatter annihilate you get about 40
to 45 kilotons
of tnt just one gram plus one gram so
two grams
so for this you just need one gram of
antimicrobial to react with one gram of
regular matter regular matter is
abundant we don't need to seek it we
don't need it costs nothing but
antimatter is the real deal
so you have one gram of antimatter you
can produce the
the enough energy the energy equivalent
of let's say around three hiroshima
nuclear weapons right
so that is the amount of energy it can
give off so yes if you have
your disposal you can make incredibly
powerful and energetic
anti-matter weapons you can do that the
question is do we do we have a means of
for producing antimatter like i said
linear colliders and atom smashers like
the lhc led the large hydrogen collider
etc they produce antimatter on a regular
basis anti-particle anti-particles
yeah
uh so that's what happens in these atoms
measures and linear colliders but the
amount of antimatter that we are able to
produce is negligible very very less i
think
anti-hydrogen has been produced
and it's very difficult to store
antimatter antimatter uh you need to
keep it in
almost perfect vacuum because if you
keep antimatter in air in in the
atmosphere it will react
with the
molecules of air
it will annihilate immediately it needs
to be in complete perfect vacuum and it
should we we also need to ensure it
doesn't touch the walls of the container
which has this vacuum
so you need magnetic confinement and all
that and it's it's very difficult to
produce any significant amount of
antimatter
so it's extremely expensive to do that
so the manhattan project
in the 1930s and 40s which produced the
first nuclear reactor in the first
nuclear weapon
its budget it cost about 30 billion
dollars in today's money approximately
30 billion dollars in today's money now
a millionth
of a gram of antimatter
a millionth one divided by one million
that much of a gram of antimatter would
cost about 60 billion dollars today
six with nine zeros at the end of it
a thousandth of a gram of antimatter
would cost about 60 trillion dollars
six with twelve zeros after it and a
single gram
one gram of antimatter would cost about
60 quadrillion dollars six
with 15 zeros after it
so as you can see
nobody has this sort of money
the amount of money that you need to
that you need in order to produce just
one gram of antimatter
and that's why even though it is
certainly possible
it's it's impractical today
today in the future in the future we may
have the technology to produce uh
more antimatter at
all at a smaller cost maybe it could
cost the same as a nuclear weapon in
that case it would be as financially
viable as building nuclear weapons and
it would uh offer significant advantages
over nuclear
uh weapons and so on but as of today
it's it's
it's prohibitively expensive to to
produce any
reasonable amount of antimatter just one
gram will cost
quadrillions of dollars right so
that's why it's not possible today
that's why it's impractical to do it
today possibly
is it possible certainly it is possible
it is certainly possible but that won't
happen in
the near future anytime in the near
future maybe in the next 50 years maybe
in the next 100 years possibly we may
have it in that case we could even use
antimatter as a rocket fuel
yeah if they
we can produce sufficient amounts of
that that would be an extremely
useful
rocket fuel extremely efficient and
effective rocket fuel
so yes theoretically possible physically
possible but practically uh but but from
the
perspective of practicality it's
extremely impractical today
in the future it may happen
aditi says how does evolution take place
what causes our biology to evolve our
journey to becoming homo sapiens
how does it take place at the atomic
level please give your views on the
ancient girl who was an inter bread of
neanderthals and dennis owens is
interbreeding possible today and do
there still exists these species in pure
form anywhere somewhere in the world
right so what is evolution evolution is
a very slow process
it's a very very slow process it doesn't
happen
or or a period of weeks or hours or
months or years
it happens over hundreds of thousands of
years
so homo sapiens our species
has been around for about 300 000 years
we have found fossils in in parts of
africa
i think in northern africa
of
homo sapiens that date back to almost
300 000 years before today three lakh
years
same species as us anatomically modern
human beings they were not different
from us from the anatomical perspective
or the species perspective they're the
same species so our species is at least
300 000 years old
and as you can see so that's the kind of
time skill it takes for evolution to
happen before that you would you would
have a
more archaic ancestral form of homo
sapiens that we don't quite know what it
was like but it would be like more
primitive not more primitive but
different different from the
evolutionary perspective you go back a
million years you have
various more archaic human species you
go back about three or so million years
you have the ancestors of humans and
chimpanzees
you go back six million years you have
the ancestors of humans chimpanzees and
gorillas as well
so evolution takes place on very long
time scales very long time scales right
how does it happen
it happens through natural selection
natural selection
so
it's essentially a slow very slow
response to the environment
when
when a child is made
it it is the combination of
genes from both parents right
it's a combination of genes from both
parents and typically what happens is
that
the
mechanism somehow it's not quite well
understood how it happens but it tends
to
take the most
advantageous traits from both parents
sometimes you get bad traits as well i
mean if somebody has some genetic defect
or some some inherited illness that also
gets passed on right
there are lots of things like hemophilia
and whatever else right asthma
leukoderma whatever so certain recessive
or or disadvantageous traits are passed
on but typically over long periods of
time what happens is that the people who
in whom
uh disadvantageous traits are passed on
they don't survive
these are disadvantages to your survival
so over hundreds of thousands of years
the genes that are disadvantageous to
your long-term survival get weeded out
in the evolutionary process
right
and the more advantageous genes are
passed on because the people who
typically are healthier have more
children and those those traits are
passed on so it's a very long process
very slow process
and it does not happen at the atomic
level it it happens at the genomic level
at the level of your dna in your
chromosomes so it is there that this
happens and the actual physical process
is the
process of combination of genes from
both parents
that's how it happens
so that is in it's it's it's very hard
to give a clear
idea
without going deep deep into molecular
biology but that is overall how it
happens
very long time scales very slow process
thousands of general it happens over
thousands of generations that certain
genes are weeded out because they are
disadvantageous
to the survival long-term survival of
the species
and
what happens is that typically over long
periods of time you adapt the species
adapt adapts in such a way that it
responds best to the environment so
let's say you are living in a very long
ice age that has been going on for 200
000 years slowly the species you will
see it will develop more hair more fur
because that gives us gives it an
advantage
oh
and it helps it survive more in cold
climate
so that's the sort of response you see
over long periods of time to the
climatic and environmental conditions
uh we know that our very deep ancestors
very ancient ancestors were fish
who lived in the oceans eventually for
whatever reason they emerged out on land
and slowly over millions of years they
developed what's called lungs they were
they developed the ability to breathe
oxygen and survive entirely on land this
happened over several millions of years
these are very slow
uh iterative responses to the
environmental changes and lifestyle
changes so that's how it happens it's a
very slow process now what about this
girl who was
like you say interbred
nenethal and this ones so
when it comes to the neanderthals and
the denisovans these are uh
subspecies
of of uh
so you have homo sapiens hormone
neanderthals homo denisovan or whatever
it is
these are sub species of human beings
just like
let me give you a very crude
approximation
we have wolves and we have the regular
dogs
kanye's lupus and kanye's lupus domestic
whatever whatever the latin name is
so the domestic dog that we have
is a subspecies of the wolf of the wild
wolf they are essentially the same
the same animal the same species but the
the domesticated the house dog or the
the dog that lives with humans is a
subspecies of the wolf they can still
interbreed and produce a very viable
offspring so what would you call them
dogs wolves doesn't matter it's it's
just a canine species
that's a very crude and rough example
you know for analogy purposes
now when it comes to humans homo sapiens
or neanderthals danish ones
we are
we know that the neanderthals went
extinct about twenty thirty thousand
years before today then they saw ones
also went extinct for whatever reason
and yet we know that there was
interbreeding between homo sapiens and
neanderthals and homo sapiens and dennis
owens and also now we know between
neanderthals and dinosaurs themselves so
the species
these three different kinds of humans
were
were genetically
close enough that they could
breed with each other and produce viable
offspring we know that most non-african
human beings
have about
four five percent
neanderthal ancestry we know that
certain populations in asia in oceania
et cetera human populations have maybe
two three four percent of daily so one
ancestry and so on
and there is some uh back reaction into
africa as well of neanderthal ancestry
it's it's a very complex
genetic landscape
uh
so
this interbreeding was possible because
these species or some subspecies were
genetically close enough which means
that last their last common ancestor was
quite recent which means that they had
not completely diverged to the extent
that they could not interbreed and
produce offspring
humans
and gorillas or humans and chimpanzees
cannot produce offspring even if they
were to try and civility for gorillas
and champions etc because it's been so
long that the genetics have diverged
significantly it's no longer possible to
produce offspring but among these three
species subspecies humans sapiens in the
thousand denisovans it was possible and
that's why you see
that we i mean
i believe in india we don't seem to have
much neanderthal ancestry for whatever
reason that's a whole different story
the aryan
invasion migration tourism picnic
uh myth but yeah
now yeah so interbreeding is possible
well we no longer have neanderthals we
no longer have the denisovans we only
have homo sapiens now
uh i don't know how it happened but we
are the only ones left and we are all
over
so how do we intervene it's not possible
because we don't have any of them to
interbreed with
uh
and so yeah that's your answer these
pieces don't exist and there is not
something as a pure species a pure
species
it doesn't make any sense there is no
such thing as a pure species uh there is
no such thing as a pure race you know
people talk about races of human beings
that's a it's an extraordinarily
unscientific idea so yeah
those species or subspecies no longer
exist and there is no such thing as pure
species and so on so forth
all right so that's the answer
akash says i read that black holes have
three properties mass charge and spin
but black holes are just a tear in the
space-time fabric so what does it really
mean that they spin and have a charge
also connected to this is what is a
schwarzschild black hole and how do we
find out the mass
of black holes when we can barely see
them all right so black holes are not
quite tears in the fabric of space-time
they're not tears or holes in space-time
they
a black hole is essentially a mass a
pure mass
that's what it is uh
so let me first go to what is the short
shield radius and all that so
the the uh
what is a schwarzschild black hole
it is an uncharged
non-rotating black hole that is what a
sorcery black hole is so the
schwarzschild solution to the einstein
field equations is
something that is in that is uncharged
and non-rotating in in a universe
without the cosmological constant that's
the schwarzschilds metric
a solution to the einstein field
equations then you have other kinds of
black holes like the reisner nordstrom
black hole which is a charged black hole
but it is not rotating then you have cur
black holes which are uncharged black
holes that are rotating that have
angular momentum and then you have
curved newman black holes that are
charged as well as rotating
these are different solutions to the
einstein
einstein field equations to the einstein
maxwell equations and so on which give
us these different kinds of black holes
so black holes
can come in these different flavors
uncharged non-rotating which are swashed
black holes
charged but non-rotating ryzen nordstrom
uncharged rotating which is cur and
charged as well as rotating current four
different major flavors or types
of black holes right so what is a black
hole a black hole is
a region in space time
that
conceals a point
from the general relative
relativity perspective it's a region in
space time that conceals
a point
that has infinite density mass density
and infinite curvature
and this is hidden behind what's called
an even horizon so it's not a tear in
the fabric of space-time but it is
something unphysical uh an infinity
is unphysical what is an infinity you
divide a number by zero that's when you
get infinity that is unphysical that
cannot happen
so that tells us that there is a flow or
defect
in the physics in the equations of
general negativity uh we need a better
theory of relativity
we need a theory of relativity that
brings that
that
is a marriage between geometric dynamics
of einstein and quantum theory quantum
field theory quantum mechanics you
combine the two you will have a proper
theory of quantum gravity in which i
believe in these singularities will no
longer occur
so from what we know today
a black hole is a regional space time
yeah it is it is an event horizon which
concedes which hides this monstrous
singularity it's not a tear in the
fabric of space-time right so that is
what it is
so
we also have something called an
extremal black hole so an extremal black
hole is an object that has the minimal
possible mass compatible with a given
amount of charge and given amount of
angular momentum
so that's an extremely black hole
and you have near external black holes
etcetera it is speculated or
hypothesized at the theorize that the
entropy of an extreme black hole could
be equal to zero and so on now the other
question is uh what
how do we find the mass
of black holes when we can barely see
them very simple newtonian mechanics
nutrient dynamics
celestial dynamics you see the effect
the black hole has on other objects
if you see a star let's say you are
talking about the star the black hole
the supermassive black hole at the
center of our own galaxy the milky way
we know where it is we don't see it it's
dark
but what do we see we see this
incredible dance that the other stars in
this region are doing around this
invisible object
we see
the speeds
the velocities of the stars
yeah these are elliptical orbits
we can
uh
deduce
the size the masses of the stars through
various means astronomical techniques
so we know there's a bunch of stars at
the very heart of our galaxy that are
doing this extraordinary dance
around an unseen object
and based on the
size
distance
speed
and time of the of the orbits and the
masses of this of the stars we can very
accurately reduce the mass of this
unseen object that is making them all
dance around
so that's how that's one way
of deducing
the mass of a black hole and there are
other ways you can use gravitational
lensing
a black hole is invisible yeah it's dark
invisible actually but it is a very
massive object which causes
light to warp around it which causes
space time to warp around it
the warping of space-time
and that's why light bends and you can
measure the bending of the light and
calculate the amount of mass of black
hole that black hole would have so there
are multiple ways of doing it and that's
how typically it is done
okay dhruva kumar says is the placebo
effect real how can anyone treat the
deceased body without medicine what's
your take on this
um the placebo effect is something that
uh that you see in medicine
so let's say you're doing a trial of a
new drug
you have uh
come up with a new drug that to to to
treat some illness yeah and you want to
do a trial so how do you do a proper
trial you take two groups of volunteers
let's say a hundred group a group of
hundred here and a hundred a group of
hundred there
you call one group group a and you call
one group group b total 200 people
divided into two groups a and b
to group a
you give
the new drug that you've developed in
this let's say in the in the form of a
pill a white pill
to so that is what you give to the
hundred people in group a this white
pill which is the new drug that you've
developed to treat whatever whatever
illness
in group b
so both these groups of people have that
illness okay which is which this drug is
supposed to treat group a takes the drug
group b you give the same kind of white
pill but it is an inactive substance it
doesn't contain the drug it doesn't
contain the medicine it is nothing it's
an inactive it's it's a
gelatin or or cellulose or whatever
something that will not react with the
body it will do nothing but you don't
tell these two groups
what they've received so both will
believe that they have taken the drug
and then over time or the certain or the
very specific period of time you see the
kind of effect this these two groups
exhibit
and that's how you can see whether a
drug is efficacious or not so that so
the tablet which contains the drug is
the actual drug and the tablet which
does nothing is called a placebo
and very often it is seen
that when you give a person a placebo
and tell them it's a drug that is going
to treat you and cure you or whatever it
actually happens it actually works it ca
so the placebo effect is real let's say
somebody is suffering from a headache
you tell them this
take this pill you'll be fine in
30 minutes
often
even though the the pill contains
nothing the headache kind of resolved
within 30 minutes or so sometimes a
person may be feeling lethargic can you
say that take this caffeine peel and
swallow it within 20 minutes you'll feel
much more active and vigorous in its
placebo very often you see that the the
person actually feels much better
after taking the placebo so this is
called the placebo effect it cannot
actually treat diseases it cannot cure
you of cancer it cannot cure heart
disease but it can have certain effects
certain very beneficial effects
sometimes even when a person knows that
they are taking a placebo
you may see this kind of effect
so uh
that's what the placebo effect is it is
like
so
it's because in certain cases
the mind the brain or whatever you want
to call it it has the
ability
to produce significant beneficial
or biochemical changes in the body which
may
uh end up
giving you a better outcome to whatever
problem you're suffering right
for instance uh the brain is capable of
releasing endorphins which are natural
painkillers
endorphins you give a person a placebo
say it's a painkiller
it may induce the brain
into releasing endorphins that have the
same effect as a painkiller and so on so
that is what the placebo effect is it is
not very well understood
it is known to work
and yeah it's one of the great mysteries
of the human brain the human
psyche the subconscious and so on so
forth
ayush says
almost all of the ed tech
views
show space time curving below a planet
or a star just like a trampoline but
there is no top or bottom in space then
does it mean that space time curves in
all directions around the planet or sir
or a star and if so
then how can a black hole have infinite
curvature of space time in all
directions
good question so yes you you
see any any popular science
tv show or documentary etc they will
show you a trampoline like surface in
which you play planet let me let's let's
see it it's all over
um
let me share my screen and let's pull
out one of these images
images
take a look at this
take a look at what they do to us see
this is your typical uh this is the way
they show it typically it's a two
dimensional surface with length and
breadth
which with this grid structure on it
this grid etched on it you place these
planets or massive objects and and you
see how space time curves
so this is how they show the curvature
of space time and the question which are
you she's asking is true is a good
question
everything is it's always shown this way
does it mean
that uh there is top and bottom in space
well it is not true this is
a misleading representation of the
curvature of space-time let me show you
a true
more accurate representation of the
curvature of space-time
take a look at this
this is how space-time actually curves
let me remove this from here take a look
this is what space time curvature should
be shown as actually
so it curves in three dimensions the
presence of mass makes
the fabric of space time the
four-dimensional fabric of space-time to
curve in this manner what we are seeing
is the curvature of the three spatial
dimensions length breadth and height
we cannot see the curvature of time
obviously because we don't have the
ability to see in four dimensions
but this is what the real curvature of
of space
looks like when it is affected by
mass
so it is not
this sort of dime curvature
two-dimensional curvature it's a
curvature of space time
so remember this meme
this mean you should remember that the
two-dimensional view is misleading it is
incorrect the three-dimensional view
is what
the curvature of space is really
like
all right
so that's what it is that's what the
curvature of space time really is like
that's how you should visualize it in
your mind's eye
um what's the question infinite
curvature yeah infinite curvature is
unphysical it doesn't make sense
so
from the perspective of general
relativity from the equations from the
solutions of the equations
it's telling us that at the heart at the
very center of a black hole behind the
invent event horizon
unseen from the
mortal eye at the very center
of this black hole of any black hole
there is a point
of infinite space-time curvature and
infinite density infinity
but infinities are unphysical
how do you
mathematically create an infinity you
take a number and divide by zero
you take one divided by zero it's
infinity you take a million divided by
zero it's infinity you take any number
divided by zero it's infinity that is
unphysical it simply cannot happen in
the real world
so what it means is that general
relativity is flawed it is incorrect it
is very accurate it has passed all tests
that we have able we have been able to
throw at it but at the microscope at the
ultra microscopic level it breaks down
the equations give us
unphysical answers singularities
infinities
which means that the theory works great
at macroscopic scales at large scales
but it breaks down at the ultra
microscopic quantum scale which means
that we need a better
version of this theory we need a quantum
theory of gravity quantum gravity and we
still don't have it
so
so that's what it is
karthik says are the conscious mind and
the subconscious mind real can you
please differentiate between them
um
yeah there does seem to be a conscious
level of existence and a subconscious
level of existence conscious mind
subconscious mind
um
the conscious mind is what we use in
doing things consciously deliberately
when we are thinking about something
when we are doing decision making
when we decide what to do when we are
learning
when we are practicing some skill we are
doing it consciously
right
let's say i'm playing golf i'm
practicing how to play golf
so in golf there is a certain swing that
you have to do right it has to go in a
certain arc
the first time you go and play golf
you're not going to be able to hit the
golf ball with your with your with your
club you're going to miss you do it
hundreds of times you're going to start
hitting the ball so you're practicing
deliberately consciously
you do it tens of thousands of times
times then you your swing is going to
get better and better and you're going
to be able to hit the ball further and
further away and you're going to be able
to
ensure that it ends up where you wanted
to end up that takes
hundreds of hours of practice tens of
thousands of swings that you practice
you're practicing deliberately
consciously but the subconscious mind is
internalizing this and it becomes part
of your muscle memory after a long
period of practice like this many months
years you can wake up in the middle of
the night and do a perfect swing without
even thinking about it
so that's where this the subconscious
mind is taken over
so you practice consciously but you
execute
using the subconscious mind that is the
key to sporting excellence
now people who get nervous
let's say you are a great
golfer
you're a great goal for you you
you execute
flawlessly in practice
but when you go for the competition
you're nervous you're nervous because
you see so many great golfers around you
you may be better than them but if you
are nervous and you you're gonna go do
your swing you're gonna again do it
consciously the key is to turn off the
conscious mind and let the subconscious
take over because the subconscious is
going to execute far better than the
conscious mind so there is a whole
mental programming that you have to
master as a support as an elite sports
person whether it is golfing whether it
is archery whether it is any other sport
you have to master the mind you have to
allow
the consciousness the subconscious mind
to take over
while performing
in competition you practice
consciously you perform you execute
by allowing the subconscious mind to
take over these are two different
aspects of mind so uh the subconscious
mind is stubborn it internalizes
internalizes things and refuses to give
them up that's why you need to
consciously ensure that your
subconscious mind
internalizes internalizes the right
things
you repeat certain negative things to
yourself over and over again
it's going to have a real effect on you
there is something called negative
self-talk and positive self-talk
if a person is a very positive person by
nature and they keep repeating to
themselves mentally i'm great i'm this
i'm that whatever it is
positive self-talk that person's
self-confidence over time will grow
better and better but a person who
constantly criticizes himself or herself
internally
all the time that internal self-talk you
keep doing it for months you're gonna
become a very diffident
low confidence person who will not
perform well in life so this is how you
train the subconscious mind through
through your self-talk through what you
choose to tell yourself over and over
again and the way you practice and so on
so that is kind of the difference
between the conscious mind and the
subconscious mind what i'm doing right
now
i'm speaking to you all i'm doing it
consciously my conscious mind is doing
it
but the habits the behavior the outlook
the attitude or whatever else is there
is because of the habits
that have been ingrained in me
by my own choice over or years yeah
so some people you feel they are very
positive
very
cheerful very joyous it's because of
their subconscious
i mean you can you can act for some time
you can pretend but you can't pretend
forever
you cannot pretend to be something else
that you are not forever eventually your
true nature comes out
similarly some people
you can sense that they are very low
confidence they are very
well
kind of negative they have a negative
um aura or whatever you want to call it
yeah whatever what you want to use so
that's because of the
subconscious shining through at times
and so on so yeah
there are no very there are no clear
scientific definitions of subconscious
conscious etc but it does exist
psychiatrists will know this
psychologists will know this and so on
so that roughly roughly is the
difference between the conscious and the
subconscious the psyche
and the actual
conscious
mind
okay shweta says
could you critique and compare gravity
newton's theory versus the fabric of
space and time which is einstein's
theory right good question what is the
difference between newtonian gravity
and einsteinian gravity which is general
relativity
that is a very good question and i'm
glad somebody asked so what is all this
stuff
um so newtonian gravity all right so
let's talk about gravity
gravity
the understanding of what gravity is was
the first big unification of the forces
what do i mean by that
we all knew our ancestors knew for
thousands of years
you take an apple you drop it it's going
to go right to the to the
ground it's going to go towards the
ground it's going to fall
all objects all massive objects fall
they fall downwards we knew this
you throw a stone in a certain direction
it's going to take a parabolic
trajectory trajectory a ballistic
trajectory is going to fall and so on we
knew this
but the big leap of imagination was when
some of our ancestors realized
that the force that thing makes things
fall
on the earth
is the same force that governs the
motions of the stars and the planets
in the sky
that leap of imagination that
realization was the first big
unification
of forces
the forces that govern us on this little
planet are the same as the forces that
govern the massive universe
the stars the galaxies
the moon
the planets the sun and the earth
that was the first big unification so we
our ancients called it gurudwakarshan in
sanskrit eventually these ideas made
their way to the west
calculus made its way to the west newton
got hold of it and he came up with the
principia mathematica in latin
the the which
also had the theory of gravitation so
newtonian gravity is what a newton came
up with we call it newton newton in
gravity and according to this
perspective on gravity gravity is a
constant instantaneous force constant
force instantaneous force action at a
distance
and it is represented by the equation f
is equal to g times m1 m2 upon r squared
the the potential is one upon r
potential the force is g m1 m2 open r
squared f is the force g is the newton
in the newton's constant m1 and m2 are
the masses of the two objects the two
massive bodies and r is the radius
the distance between the centers of the
two masses that is the newtonian gravity
in very brief it's an instantaneous
force it's a constant force it's an
attractive force yeah a pulling force
its action at a distance
that is neutron and gravity
einstein's gravity
way went way beyond that einstein
this
demonstrated he
theorized
that gravity this what we perceive as
the force of gravity is actually the
curvature of not only space but time the
four dimensional
structure fabric of space-time so when
you have a mass
in
space or space-time the presence of the
mass
causes the fabric of space-time to curve
to bend to distort mass curves
space-time and the curvature of
space-time tells mass how to move
so it's it works both ways
so this is the geometric theory of
gravity
geometry dynamics which is general
relativity which einstein came up with
in 1915 and it has been tested
thousands of times the objective of all
these tests is to prove this theory
wrong in different ways and thus far all
the tests have failed this theory works
it's the best theory that we have at
large distances
in the macroscopic uh sphere of the
world domain of the world
that's the main difference between uh
general derivative general relativity
and neutron and gravity
another big difference
is that in newton's perspective
gravity is an instantaneous force action
at a distance infinite range
in
the einsteinian perspective the better
perspective
there is a speed limit it's not
instantaneous the curvature of
space-time doesn't happen
instantaneously it has a speed limit
c the speed of light
and let me illustrate this
let me illustrate this by going to my
where is the image once again
let's do a thought experiment my dear
friends i always talk about thought
experiments let's do a thought
experiment
this here
is our beloved home
system the solar system
at the center you have the sun
then you have the different planets
mercury venus earth mars
the asteroid belt and then jupiter is
cyto uranus neptune and how dare they
not throw pluto anyway
this is the solar system right now let's
do a
thought experiment
let's say by magic
i make the sun disappear
the sun at the center of the solar
system i make it vanish all of a sudden
by magic
then what happens
according to new according to newton's
perspective
gravity
is what
keeps the solar system together because
of the grav the enormous gravity in the
mass of the sun
if the sun were to suddenly disappear
all the planets would immediately fly
off in different directions because this
great
mass that is holding them together is
gone
so if you were to make the sun disappear
according to newton all these planets
would immediately
fly off into outer space in different
directions
now
according to the einstein
version of gravity the better version of
gravity there is a speed limit
if the sun were to disappear
we know that it takes light eight
minutes roughly
to travel from the sun to the earth so
even if the sun were to disappear
on earth we would know not know about
this for eight minutes
for eight minutes we would still imagine
we would still believe the sun is still
there because we are still getting the
light that uh was emitted eight minutes
ago it's only after eight minutes that
we on earth would realize that the sun
has disappeared and it's only after
eight minutes that the earth would start
flying off in a different direction
it would take longer for that to happen
to mars
much longer for jupiter saturn uranus
neptune pluto and so on
so it is the inner planets that would
start flying off
first
and slowly slowly one by one the outer
planet planets will go off in different
directions once the gravitational effect
of the sun
disappears at the speed of light
so this is the major difference very
very significant difference between
newtonian gravity and einstein's general
theory of relativity and the general
theory of relativity is the better
superior version we know that
so that in brief is
the major
differences
soros says how legitimate is psychiatry
as a profession i read somewhere that
one in seven people in india
are suffering from an undiagnosed mental
illness
that said
is it in any way factual or a survey
meant for the big farmer's profits
also considering the opioid crisis which
keeps coming in the news okay hold on
a psychiatry well um psychiatry is kind
of hand waving in voodoo
see
let's say you are an orthopedic surgeon
doctor
how do you know something is wrong you
take a look at let's say a person comes
with a broken arm and you want to fix it
you're going to take an x-ray you're
going to see exactly what the affected
part of the body looks like right let's
say somebody has a kidney problems
you're gonna scan the kidney you're
gonna go do a whole bunch of tests and
you're gonna figure out exactly what is
wrong with that kidney
let's say you are an eye specialist
you're gonna look at the eye and see
what's wrong with the eye and so on and
so forth
you're a gastrointestinal doctor surgeon
whatever you're gonna do tests and image
do imaging of the object of the of the
stomach of the intestines etc and then
diagnose what's wrong with the with the
person
when it comes to psychiatrists they are
diagnosing
brain problems mind problems
how do they do it do they ever take a
look at the brain
no
psychiatrists are the only
members of the medical profession that
never take a look
at the organ that is affected which is
the brain
so how do they make the diagnosis they
talk to the patient they tell the
patient to lie down on a couch on a sofa
or whatever it is
the patient lies down the psychiatrist
typically sits on a different chair next
to the person and then asks questions
interviews the person tells the person
to tell stories about their life or
whatever it is
and then this happens over multiple
sessions or a long period of time
eventually the psychiatrist makes
certain assessments tries to
to tease out certain symptoms or
clusters clusters of symptoms and based
on this very rough
procedure they uh
diagnose what is wrong with the person
and prescribe various medications
it is hand waving and voodoo
that's what it is that's what psychiatry
is what should actually happen is at
least do imaging
of the brain
very often what happens is that people
have
undiagnosed
brain injuries
it happens very often you know brain
injury when we typically think of a
brain injury we
we see
in our mind's eye a person falling down
a flight of stairs and hitting their
head on the floor or a person falling
from a tree and hitting their head on
the ground or a person playing american
football and being hit in the head
repeatedly time after time after time or
or a person cricket and being hit by a
cricket ball you have a concussion so
this is how we imagine a brain injury to
happen and often that's how it happens a
kid at the age of three fell down
was unconscious for five minutes then he
grew up it was fine and everything went
back to normal but you that may have
resulted in a brain injury
the person seems to be normal the kid
grows up but over time they
they show
they exhibit symptoms of mental illness
it could be because of a brain injury
but because the kid just
did not appear to be ill
it was forgotten
these things happen very happen very
often in the case of the opioid crisis
like you mentioned drug abuse etc drug
abuse
damages the brain
long-term drug abuse whatever drug
you're using hard drugs whatever it is
it ends up damaging people's brains
but that is never seen it's not visible
to anyone the person looks just not just
fine
so uh
i would say that psychiatrists should
add certain tools to their arsenal
they should do a brain imaging
there is something called spect imaging
spect single photon emission
computerized thermography
spect imagine imaging should be done
which essentially gives you a good scan
of how the brain is what are the regions
of the brain that are active that are
showing more activity which are the ones
that are showing less activity is there
any damage in the brain and so on you
can see that
so that would actually give you an idea
of whether a person actually has
any brain injury or whether there are
regions of the brain that are
hyperactive there is something called
ocd obsessive compulsive disorder
in which the the brain refuses to to
[Music]
to calm down
you have parts of the brain in the front
the frontal lobes that are hyperactive
typically in a healthy brain the back of
the brain needs to be needs to show more
activity the front another part of the
brain should be showing low activity
in ocd you have
the frontal lobes etc that show very
high activity and so on
so if you do this sort of imaging spect
imaging or whatever else then you can
get a good idea of what's actually
happening because sometimes you have
people which show the same symptoms but
they have very different brain scans
so this so what needs to happen is that
psychiatry needs to
needs to actually use some imaging
technique techniques psychiatrists need
to be trained in all of these things
they should be trained into how about
how to read brain scans what brain scans
to to to
to prescribe
and then based on
this
more solid
observational data scientific data on
the basis of that
uh they should make their diagnosis and
they should prescribe medicines right
now it's all voodoo and hand waving they
they sometimes
prescribe behavior therapy that can be
very cruel
someone's suffering from
a brain injury which is exhibiting
itself in a certain range of symptoms
but you are
prescribing
behavioral therapy to correct the
behavior the behavior is an outcome of
the injury you have to treat the injury
not the symptom so that's how it is
right now i would say psychiatry is just
hand waving in voodoo i do not even
consider it to be science
that is my assessment of psychiatry it
is not science it is hand waving and
voodoo that's all it is
an amazing indian citizen
says why has india lost the speed in the
global super computer race india has
never really invested
in super computing i think if you look
at the i don't know what the rate
rankings are right now if you look at
the top 100 super computers in the world
i think india would have two or three of
those in the 90s so india has never
really
tried to participate as a serious player
in this big race uh
most of the
top 10 top 20 top 30 super computers
were american chinese or maybe japanese
maybe a couple of
british and french super computers maybe
something from israel perhaps but the
top three major players are the us china
and japan
india is not even trying to participate
and you know it's not that hard to build
a supercomputer you can build a
supercomputer on the cheap if you know
how to do it
you have to cannibalize existing uh
existing computers so what is a
supercomputer a supercomputer is a very
powerful machine computer with extremely
high processing power parallel
processing
very high flops teraflops
uh
what's the flop floating operations per
second teraflops is
it in the 10 raised to what um
megaflops is generous to six
gigaflops is tennis nine
teraflops beta flops and so on so very
high processing power right that's what
it is uh
like i said it's process it's possible
to build yourself a super computer on
the cheap all you have to do you have to
spend some money of course but not the
kind of billions of dollars you would
imagine
all you should you have to do is you
know what a ps5 is playstation 5. a
playstation 5 has extremely high
processing power
buy a thousand of those yeah it's
expensive but it's not as expensive as
building a super computer
uh what does a ps5 cost fifty thousand
rupees
you buy ten of that it's five lakh
hundred is fifty lakhs so
a thousand of these would cost about
five crore rupees
you take them apart
take the processors you need to do some
hacking some some black magic obviously
computer black magic and you tie these
processes together you bring them
together
and make them process in parallel there
you have your own super computer very
powerful support computer
so it's been done people have done this
with the ps2 20 30 years ago 20 years
ago ps2 was the older one of the older
versions of the playstation
it was possible to take 100 ps2s
together
piece them together and create a super
computer out of that a very good
supercomputer so it's possible to do
this on the fly on the cheap
i say why can't the iits have a yearly
budget
and a yearly competition the indian
institutes of technology which are
currently investing in the humanities
for for whatever reason
eliminate the humanities departments
iits are for technology not for
humanities use that money invest it in a
yearly competition every
uh
every iit gets a certain amount of money
a few crore rupees to build their own
supercomputer
yeah you have one year every year to do
this
and then at the end of the year we're
going to compete
which super computer among all the iits
has the best power the best uh
is the is the most powerful
and then you get a big prize and you can
start your own startup or whatever
why can't we do that sort of thing
it's not that expensive
it it takes a little bit of leadership
and vision which we are currently
lacking
our iit's our
all the the entire academic system is
run by people with a bureaucratic
mindset
people who want status quo people who
are not ambitious unfortunately that's
what's happening
all it we have the money in the country
we have the money
it's just the mindset that's that's
problematic
it will take a little bit of leadership
and a little bit of ambition to change
this entirely
and of course now we have ai we have
machine learning we have neural networks
we can use all that on super computers
we also have quantum computing i don't
think we are doing anything in india
vis-a-vis this new emerging field of
quantum computing quantum computing is
not that easy you need extremely low
temperatures to to have a quantum
computer because you need to
create quantum super superpositions and
sustain the superpositions in order to
do quantum computations using qubits so
that is a different field you need
cryogenic temperatures for that
so at least
i mean that also should be certainly
invested in i think there was some
initiative but the amount of money they
were putting into it was laughable
unfortunately
so
india can still become a major global
power in supercomputers in quantum
computing in the next 10 years
provided we we have the right leadership
and and the right attitude in the right
ambition and we do some restructuring of
our academic institutions it's very much
possible it's still possible today
let's see
chetan says
since we humans aren't centrally
connected
how is it that we all have unique
fingerprints and dna apart from
identical twins in some cases is it
possible that two people can have the
same fingerprint uh i'm not sure how
fingerprints are created i think there's
some there's a
uh
i don't think there's an exact code for
your exact precise fingerprint in your
dna it's something that happens i'm not
sure what the process biological process
is that gives rise to everyone's unique
fingerprints what we do know
is that uh
fingerprints are reasonably unique
uh 1 in 10 million
so if you take 10 million people
the probability is that only that
roughly maybe 6 million maybe 4 million
maybe 10 million i'm just giving you a
ballpark figure
so the probability let's say it's 10
million so the probability is that
if you take any random 10 million people
let's say
all of them will have unique
fingerprints but if you take 20 million
people
maybe two of them will have fingerprints
that match
so i think and the same goes for dna
dna fingerprinting the old term for the
technique
uh
so
if you have a population of seven what
is the population of the earth now seven
billion
some people will have
fingerprints that match and some people
will have dna that match
so let's say the chance is one in 10
million then in a country like india
with 1.4 billion people
there could be a 140 people that have
the same dna as me and the same
fingerprint as me it is possible
and if you look at the entire population
of the world you have to multiply by by
a certain figure and you will come so
dna is not entirely unique
it is possible that people just randomly
may have the same dna and the same
fingerprints
it is possible statistically it is
possible
that's all i can offer you i'm not sure
how exactly it happens that you are
using younger unique fingerprints are
created i'm not sure what the process
behind that is
maybe if you
if you look into the biological uh
dynamics mechanics of this you may get
an idea of how it happens
udit says what would be the reaction of
space core from different countries if
they found multicellular organisms on
other planets
um um
i think only one nation that i know of
has a space core there is the united
states a space force
which is uh which is a branch of the us
military
uh the u.s space force was created on
the orders of uh
the 45th president mr trump
um
i'm not sure if the chinese have a space
force space corps whatever you want to
call it if they do then maybe two
countries of it india doesn't have a
space
force officially
and so on
so let's talk about what would the
reaction from the scientific community
in different countries
um let's say we find
unmistakable undeniable evidence of
multicellular primitive microorganisms
on let's say titan or let's say
enceladus or europa
or pluto or maybe mars maybe venus
what would be the reaction firstly
not a great deal of surprise
but very high amount of excitement that
would be
incredible the first time in human
history we have discovered this so the
excitement levels will go through the
roof surprise not so much
because i think it's quite likely
if you if you
from the from the
biological perspective it's reasonably
likely that there could be
primitive microbial life on these
various
parts of the solar system
so uh
multi-cellular organisms like microbial
animals that would not be a great cause
of concern
that would not cause a great amount of
surprise it would create crows grows
great excitement
and microbial life doesn't pose any kind
of threat
to our planet to our species to our uh
ecosystem environment so yeah it would
not cause any any major concern
yeah
but yes it would it would uh make us see
the universe in a whole different light
that yes now we know there is light
there is life apart in in places other
than the earth
which could indicate that life is quite
common so i think it could perhaps be a
matter of time that we detect something
in the next half century hundred years
maybe in our own solar system it's
possible it's possible there could be
microbial life
intelligent life is a whole different
thing that would set off all kinds of
alarm bells
intelligent life is
potential danger you have to treat it as
a potential danger let's say you're
walking in a forest in the middle of the
night complete darkness and you see
somebody approaching you
what's going to be your initial reaction
fear
your hair will stand up
goosebumps your immediate reaction is
going to be fear unless you don't care
for your own survival because in the
dark forest when you see something
approaching you you have to assume it's
going to be a threat to you that's the
only way you can ensure a survival
that's the dark forest theory or world
view which says the entire universe is
like a dark forest everyone's hiding
because they know
any potential
intelligent life that you encounter
could be a
could be a a mortal threat for you
so uh if we encounter if we discover
microbial life
multicellular organisms it's not going
to be a cause of concern if you detect
science of intelligent life that is
incredibly dangerous so whole different
perspective
but yeah you discover life even
microbial life it tells you there's a
high likelihood that there could be more
evolved life in other places
which again
should elevate your threat status
akar says do you think coding
programming is becoming or will become
an absolute skill in the near future
i've seen experts on both sides of the
arguments some claim that it's an
essential skill that should be tossed to
every child right from an early age just
like math
others say this idea is being blown out
of proportion
i think the reaction and the response
and the kind of
argument that you see depends on the age
of whom you're asking older people will
typically say it's not important
younger people will say it's an integral
part of the future
so how do we see this
it depends are computers gonna be around
forever in for the foreseeable future
yes
are most problems in the world now being
solved via computers and why are we
programming
yes
from that perspective one would have to
say
that yes
coding programming is going to be
important
quite important
it's a skill that is
as easy to learn as mathematics it's
just logic
in a certain way obviously some people
will have a better aptitude
some people may not be so good at it
naturally
inclined to that and so on but as long
as computers
are going to be a part of the future as
long as more and more problems are going
to be solved
through programming through coding
through computers
through software
as long as that sort of future is in the
offing
i think coding and programming is
something that we need to inculcate in
children who want to do well in life
uh
of course uh
manufacturing and all those
other skills are also important without
that you cannot build computers and so
on research is important
but when it comes to problem solving
it's all about solving problems today
more many of the world's problems many
of society's problems
can be solved
through computing
through computers
so as long as that happens computing i
mean coding and programming is going to
be very important
so
i think we can all envisage a world in
which computers
become more and more an integral part of
our life
they become ubiquitous
we will have augmented reality we'll be
able to wear glasses that show us a
whole lot more about the world that we
can see right now
if that future is the future which it
seems to be
then computing then programming and
coding is going to be important
so i think that yes it is a good bet
from my perspective
that programming and computing is going
to be an essential skill
if you want to do well in life you need
to have that in your skill set you may
want to be a philosopher you may want to
be a poet you may want to be
somebody who tinkers with physical
equipment
or you maybe want to be a teacher etc
even in those occupations
programming
could be an asset so yes overall i would
agree with the with the camp that with
those who are in the camp that says that
programming and coding is important it's
going to be a very very valuable skill
in the future so yeah i agree with that
sort of says there's a big debate about
what depression actually is whether it's
a mere chemical fluctuation or something
deep-rooted which also involves
sociological factors
uh do indian medical systems like
ayurveda have definitions of depression
and other psychiatric illness in general
um depression could have a physical
cause like i like i mentioned some time
ago somebody has an undiagnosed brain
injury somebody is a tumor that that's
growing in the brain somebody has a cyst
in the brain that can affect the brain
chemistry the brain functions that can
cause a very strange behavior or
abnormal behavior that can manifest
itself as depression or something worse
yeah
so yeah that can have chemical
uh causes
on the other hand there are people who
have completely normal
uh
brain function that also have depression
what is the cause of that there are
certain scientists
who like to say that all emotions and
thoughts are chemical reactions there is
a hyper simplistic and idiotic
view of the world we don't understand
anything about the brain
we understand next to nothing about it
about it
we don't know where consciousness comes
from we don't know really where the
emotions come from yes it's possible to
modulate emotions
using chemicals
uh there are certain
drugs that are available for for uh
depression i'm not sure what it's called
prozac is it and there are there are
things like dmt like lsd that cause
various
brain reactions and and
feelings of euphoria and so on these are
drugs so yes you can certainly affect
the change the mood emotions well-being
mental well-being emotional well-being
using chemistry using chemicals but that
doesn't solve the long-standing problems
that a person may have
so we don't know
what depression is
we don't know what it is but there is
something called schizophrenia paranoid
schizophrenia all kinds of mental
problems some of them could have a
physical cause and actual
cause
alzheimer's disease is obviously a
deterioration of the brain tissue
but yeah it's still something that's not
very well understood
i would disagree that everything is
about chemistry i don't agree with that
uh do indian systems like ayurveda have
definitions of the depression i am not
sure about that we have lost a lot of
our information and data about ayurveda
uh so yeah we don't know much about this
unfortunately but i would not agree
there is no clear definition of
depression maybe depression comes in
various there could be multiple causes
of depression
uh
sometimes depression is caused by
external factors the circumstances in a
person's life if a person sees no hope
is trapped in a hopeless situation that
can certainly cause depression of the
loss of will to live and so on so it has
multiple causes there could be chemical
causes there could be physiological
causes that could be external causes
it's a very complex topic so that is
what i can say about this
right
t1 says does india need more computer
science engineers or more physics
professors or physicists very nice way
of putting me on the spot yeah
look the world needs india needs more
engineers
whether it's computer science engineers
whether it's actual
civil engineers or whatever other
engineers
progress
happens through technology technology is
developed through engineering
the concepts
are
what comes out of physics the conceptual
breakthroughs
quantum mechanics relativity which is
all being used in various technologies
today that came from theoretical physics
so all the major conceptual
breakthroughs happen through theoretical
physics typically
then it makes its way into experimental
physics like nuclear physics nuclear
reactors and all and eventually
technologies come out of it and they
spin off into the civilian sphere
so typically theoretical physics is
about 50 to 100 years ahead
of any
actual engineering application and
technological application
without physicists these things can't
happen but the actual work of bringing
this technology to the to the society is
done by engineers
so maybe we need one person physicists
and 99 engineers
that's the or maybe two person
physicists and 98 energy engineers
engineering is something that doesn't
take a lot
of
well what's the word to use intelligence
uh maybe you do need to be very
intelligent to engineers as well but
yeah it's a certain aptitude
and
typically the kind of um
yeah so i would say two person
physicists and 98 percent engineers
that's what the world needs and that's
what india needs india needs lot more
engineers a lot more engineers
to build the nation all over again yeah
right
um what else do we have
yash says what's the difference between
intuitive understanding and mathematical
understanding is mathematical
understanding opposite of in
intuitive understanding
where we cannot apply one and use the
other
you know there are two kinds of
scientists two kinds of mathematicians
there is one kind of mathematician who
takes a big problem
and he or she
uses the entire toolkit toolkit of
mathematics at their disposal to kind of
try and solve the problem use
differential equations use linear
algebra use whatever else you know
matrices whatever
uh number theory and so on
galwa theory whatever you use the entire
toolkit
though entire corpus of mathematical
knowledge that you have
and you try to make progress towards
solving that problem that is
mathematical and understanding
logic pure logic codified in the form of
mathematics there's a different kind of
mathematician as well
a very rare kind of mathematician they
see the solution first
and then they have to they know what the
solution is it appears to them in their
in their mind's eye intuitively
ramanujan used to say that it was his
goddess namagiri used to come to him in
his dreams and give him these incredible
equations that people are still
researching
so there is this and there is there was
somebody like john forbes nash
the great normal price winner who won a
nobel prize in economics for the nash
equilibrium he was that kind of a
mathematician he also unfortunately
suffered from schizophrenia for some
time
so
there's this very rare genius level
mathematician who sees the solution the
answer
first they know it's right
and it's always proven to be right
eventually
they see the answer first they write it
down or whatever and then they have to
spend
weeks months maybe years
figuring out the mathematical proof that
proves that their answer is correct
that is the difference between intuitive
understanding
and mathematical understanding intuitive
understanding is a lot all about flashes
of insight wow oh yeah that has to be
true i know it's true my gut tells me
it's true and then i have to find a way
of actually proving it through
mathematical logic
right
that's the difference
okay let's take a couple of
live chat questions we are almost at the
end of today's thing
uh today's a session
if you have questions
let me know in the live chat
questions about science technology etc
okay there's an interesting pattern
interesting perspective here
not intuition but seeing patterns and
putting those patterns together on paper
intuition comes from
internalizing a lot of patterns you
don't become a genius level
mathematician just because you're born
intelligent
you have to spend hundreds of hours
thousands of hours
studying mathematics when you spend
hundreds and thousands of words studying
mathematics solving problems
those
mathematical patterns that get ingrained
into your subconscious mind
and that's what gives you
that's how you earn those genius level
flashes of insight because of all the
patterns you have internalized that is
also your intuition you go somewhere you
know something is wrong get out of here
that's also intuition you don't you
cannot see something is wrong but it's
your ingrained
ability to recognize patterns
that tells you that something is off in
some situation so yes it's about
patterns but you have to earn
the ability
to recognize those patterns and to gain
those flashes of insight through
incredible amounts of hard work
right
um
what's the god particle it's not a
particle that came from some god
this term the god particle was coined by
some some science journalists or some
journalist the god part the so-called
gods particle is the missing boson the
higgs boson that imparts mass to the
universe
so it was a
it's its existence was theorized maybe
50 or so years ago by peter higgs
and
particle physicists have been searching
for it ever since and it's only in the
last decade in the past few years that
it was actually discovered in the large
hadron collider so it is
in quantum field theory
every
fundamental particle
has its own field it's let's say you
have protons protons are essentially
nothing but excitations in the proton
field electrons are local excitations in
the electron field that permeates the
entire universe
the protons in my body
are part of an infinite field that
permeates the entire universe and it is
the field of the protons similarly there
is a higgs field that permeates the
entire universe and the particles that
interact with the higgs field
or
the higgs boson which is a local
excitation of that field
the particles that interact with the
higgs field
acquire mass
and the particles which are
to interact with the higgs field
remain
massless
that's
the higgs field the higgs particle the
higgs boson and that's what some
journalists i believe called the god
particle so now everyone thinks it's
some supernatural thing or something no
it's not
no it's not
okay let us take maybe a couple of
questions more
um
is our universe in an atom
is our universe is
one could think of it as some kind of
atomic thing yeah possibly from a
certain perspective possibly some people
ask whether the universe is a black hole
we are all inside a black hole well you
know there are problems with that sort
of um
scenario because first of all the
universe is expanding if you have a
black hole it's not expanding
yeah we have the expansion of the fabric
of space time we know it's happening
inside a black hole there is no such
process
so that's our thing and once again
the atomic thing is also one interesting
way to look look at it if you are a high
school student but not quite
okay is there any other
interesting question
grandfather paradox look at my previous
one of my previous episodes i have gone
into that in detail
do a live session this is a live session
we are live
hello this is live i'm talking live this
is not this is not recorded
maybe you're saying video session is
that what you're saying
well that is problematic
why are video chat sessions problematic
because
firstly uh i don't get to select the
questions so very often you have
questions that have already been
answered lots of times people ask me all
over again so that doesn't give provide
value to you the audience it provides
value to the person who's asking the
question only to one person my
intent in doing all of this is to
provide some genuine value to as many
people as possible
i can do that by picking new questions
each time
in these video chat sessions what
happens very often is that i get
repeated questions that have been
answered many times secondly some people
want to ask multiple questions they want
to spend as much time as possible on the
screen with me
i i have nothing against that but i want
to give a chance to as many people as
possible in as short time as possible so
it doesn't always work that way in video
video chat sessions so that's why i have
stopped doing that maybe i will bring
that back again sometime in the future
if there is if all of you want it i can
do it do you want it let me know in the
comments below not in the live chat in
the comments below once this session is
over
all right with that i think we should
bring an end to the session we have
again crossed two hours always fun on
setting all of your questions i did a
twitter session there before yesterday i
think that was great fun a lot of
questions a lot of interesting questions
so maybe i will do that again next week
a twitter session in which i will answer
your questions through tweets
um so yeah
so that brings us to the end of today's
session thank you very much all of you
great talking to you all and i will see
you in tomorrow's session until that
until that
until then
thank you take care bye